Guide to the Simon Newton Dexter papers, 1785-1862.
Dexter, Simon Newton papers, 1785-1862.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Simon Newton Dexter papers, 1785-1862.
753
Simon Newton Dexter.
12.8 cubic ft; 9 v.; 4 rolls microfilm.
Correspondence, accounts, orders, receipts, notes, contracts, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, accounts, orders, receipts, notes, contracts, and other papers relating to Dexter's business and political activities.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Merchant, banker, Erie Canal commissioner, and cotton and woolen manufacturer.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, accounts, orders, receipts, notes, contracts, and other papers relating to Dexter's business and political activities. Many of the papers relate to the Oriskany Manufacturing Company, a woolen manufacturing firm. Other papers relate to Dexter's activities as commissioner of the Erie Canal, to local and New York State politics, and to various businesses and industries such as dry goods, cotton manufacturing, sheep raising, ironmongery, a distillery, a tannery, wholesale and retail merchants, railroads, and banks. Includes material concerning Thomas R. Gold and his family; Porteus B. Root as a contractor for the Black River Canal and a builder of plank roads; Black River Woolen Company; Detroit Farmers' and Mechanics' Bank; Dexter Manufacturing Company; Dexter Village Society; Elgin Manufacturing Company; Galena and Chicago Rail Road Company; Oneida Manufacturing Company; Rock Bottom Factory of Stowe, Mass.; and Williams Woolen Company. Correspondents include E. Bacon, Edward Bates, Francis Bicknell, John Brinckerhoff, E. Capron, Seth Capron, A. J. Center, William M. Cheever, James Cooper, Oliver Culver, John Devereux, Nicholas Devereux, J. W. Doolittle, William Durer, Guy Foote, James Goss, Francis Granger, P. L. Green, Ephraim and Roswell Hart, Hiram Holcomb, C. L. Holley, Myron Holley, Alfred Hovey, O. Hungerford, Benjamin S. Huntington, S. P. Germain, Alexander B. Johnson, Hiram Ketchum, E. Kirby, G. A. Lansing, William M. Larrabee, Sam Lawrence, Daniel Lee, and Edwin C. Litchfield
Correspondents also include, T. W. Lockwood, E. T. Throop Martin, Simon Matteson, Charles Moseley, Isaac Northrup, George W. Patterson, John B. Pease, George T. Perry, Jonas Pratt, Thadeus Pomeroy, Benjamin Poor, Josiah Porter, Henry S. Randall, B. W. Raymond, R. J. Renwick, P. V. Rogers, James Satterlee, Peter B. Schenck, Alexander Seward, Charles and Henry Seymour, C. S. Shurman, Derick Sibley, Theodore Sill, John Slade, Ambrose Spencer, J. A. Spencer, Theodore Spencer, J. D. Steele, B. F. Stillman, William M. Tallman, Comfort Tyler, Stephen Van Rensselaer, Abraham Varick, Charles D. and William Walcott, A. J. Waldron, Ezra Weeks, John A. and W. B. Welles, Edward A. Wetmore, Andrew White, John Williams, Samuel Woodsworth, and R. L. Yarwood.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Dexter, Simon Newton.; Bacon, E.; Bates, Edward.; Bicknell, Francis.; Brinckerhoff, John.; Capron, E.; Capron, Seth.; Center, A. J.; Cheever, William M.; Cooper, James.; Culver, Oliver.; Devereux, John.; Devereux, Nicholas.; Doolittle, J. W.; Durer, William.; Foote, Guy.; Germain, S. P.; Gold family.; Gold, Thomas R.; Goss, J. W.(James W.); Granger, Francis.; Green, P. L.; Hart, Ephraim.; Hart, Roswell.; Holcomb, Hiram.; Holley, C. L.; Holley, Myron, 1779-1841.; Hovey, Alfred.; Hungerford, O.; Huntington. Benjamin S.; Johnson, Alexander B.; Ketchum, Hiram.; Kirby, E.; Lansing, G. A.; Larrabee, William M.; Lawrence, Samuel.; Lee, Daniel.; Litchfield, Edwin C.; Lockwood, T. W.; Martin, E. T. Throop.; Matteson, Simon.; Moseley, C. W. R. D.(Charles W. R. D); Northrup, Isaac.; Patterson, George W.; Pease, John B.; Perry, George T.; Pomeroy, Thadeus.; Poor, Benjamin.; Porter, Josiah.; Pratt, Jonas.; Randall, Henry S.; Renwick, R. J.; Rogers, P. V.; Root, Porteus B.; Satterlee, James.; Schenck, Peter B.; Seward, Alexander.; Seymour, Charles.; Seymour, Henry.; Shurman, C. S.; Sibley, Derick.; Sill, Theodore.; Slade, John.; Spencer, Ambrose.; Spencer, J. A.; Spencer, Theodore.; Steele, J. D.; Stillman, B. F.; Tallman, William M.; Taymond, B. W.; Tyler, Comfort.; Van Rensselaer, Stephen.; Varick, Abraham.; Walcott, Charles D.; Walcott, William.; Waldron, A. J.; Weeks, Ezra.; Welles, John A.; Welles, W. B.; Wetmore, Edward A.; White, Andrew.; Williams, John.; Woodsworth, Samuel.; Yarwood, R. L.; Birmingham Manufacturing Company.; Black River Canal.; Black River Woolen Company.; Detroit Farmers' and Mechanics' Bank.; Dexter Manufacturing Company.; Dexter Village Society.; Elgin Manufacturing Company.; Erie Canal.; Galen and Chicago Rail Road Company.; Oneida Manufacturing Company.; Oriskany Manufacturing Company.; Rock Bottom Factory (Stowe, Mass.); Williams Woolen Company.
Subjects:
Politics, practical--New York (State); Iron mines and mining--New York (State); Wool industry--New York (State); Banks and banking--New York (State)--Utica.; Dry-goods--New York (State); Sheep industry--New York (State); Distilleries--New York (State); Tanneries--New York (State); Railroads--New York (State); Plank roads--New York (State); Industries--New York (State); Bankers.; Industrialists.
Places:
Jefferson County (N.Y.)--Commerce.; Whitestown (N.Y.)--Commerce.; New York (State)--Economic conditions.; Oneida County (N.Y.)--Politics and government.
Form and Genre Terms:
Account books.; Accounts.; Receipts.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Link to a more detailed finding aid.
  All the material in the collection may not be covered by this guide.
- 1793-1807 (Box 1)
- 1808-1818 (Box 2)
- 1819-1820 (Box 3)
- 1821 (Box 5)
- 1822-Oct. 1823 (Box 4)
- 1841-1870, printed material (see list in accession folder) (Box 23)
- Nov. 1823-1824 (Box 6)
- 1825-1826 (Box 7)
- 1827-1828 (Box 8)
- 1828-1831 (Box 9)
- 1832-1838 (Box 10)
- 1839 (Box 11)
- 1840 (Box 12)
- 1841 (Box 13)
- 1842-1845 (Box 14)
- 1846-1848 (Box 15)
- 1849-1850 (Box 16)
- 1851-1853 (Box 17)
- 1854 (Box 18)
- 1855-1856 (Box 19)
- 1857-1859 (Box 20)
- 1860-1905, incomplete (Box 21)
- Undated (Box 22)
- Periodicals (Box 24)
- Pamphlets (Box 25)
- Account books, bank books, two receipt books for contracts in connection with work on the enlargement of the Erie Canal, Feb.1-June 7, 1841 and June 7-Sept. 17, 1841 (see accession folder for detailed list) (Box 26)
- Newspapers and periodicals (Box 27)
- Newspapers and printed material (Box 28)
- Broadsides, maps, music, etc. (see list in accession folder) (Box 29)
- Family photos, news clippings in scrapbook (Box 30)
- Bills, receipts (Box 31)
- 7 volumes (see list in accession folder) (Box 32)
- Correspondence, 1800-1860, on microfilm (see list in accession folder) (Reel 1)
- Correspondence, 1800-1860, on microfilm (see list in accession folder) (Reel 2)